<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<articles>
  <article articleId="1" Name="Survey-Finds-Patient-Engagement-Can-Improve-Outcomes-for-Parkinson's" >
    <Title>Survey Finds Patient Engagement Can Improve Outcomes for Parkinson's</Title>
    <metaKeywords></metaKeywords>
    <metaDescription></metaDescription>
    <Header>
      <![CDATA[Survey Finds Patient Engagement Can Improve Outcomes for Parkinson's"]]>
    </Header>
    <ShortContent>
      <![CDATA[Infographic provides dynamic look at survey's topline results.]]>
    </ShortContent>
    <Content>
      <![CDATA[
        <p>A recent survey of more than 1,500 Parkinson's disease patients, caregivers and physicians conducted by Harris Poll on behalf of The Michael J. Fox Foundation and AbbVie reveals that information and specialized care can help patients become more engaged in their own treatment and in the Parkinson's disease community.</p>
        <p>The below infographic provides a dynamic look at the survey's topline results:</p>
        <img src="https://www.michaeljfox.org/files/140902_PatientEngagement_jcf.png" alt="Patient Engagement In Parkinsons's Care Can Improve Outcomes For All"/>
      ]]>
    </Content>
    <ArticleDate>2014-09-09T00:00:00.000000-05:00</ArticleDate>
    <ArticleAuthor>Partners in Parkinson's</ArticleAuthor>
    <ArticleImage><img src="https://www.michaeljfox.org/files/140902_PatientEngagement_jcf.png" alt="Patient Engagement In Parkinsons's Care Can Improve Outcomes For All"/></ArticleImage>
  </article>




  <article articleId="2" Name="Parkinson's-Organizations-Unite-to-Serve-Pateients-and-Families-Through-National-Partners-in-Parkinson's-Initiative" >
    <Title>Parkinson's Organizations Unite to Serve Pateients and Families Through National "Partners in Parkinson's" Initiative</Title>
    <metaKeywords></metaKeywords>
    <metaDescription></metaDescription>
    <Header>
      <![CDATA[Parkinson's Organizations Unite to Serve Pateients and Families Through National "Partners in Parkinson's" Initiative]]>
    </Header>
    <ShortContent>
      <![CDATA[Initiative to optimize patient care spearheaded by AbbVie and The Michael J. Fox Foundation to visit 11 cities in 2014.]]>
    </ShortContent>
    <Content>
      <![CDATA[
        <p><strong>NEW YORK, NY, JULY 21, 2014 </strong>&mdash; National Parkinson's organizations are working together to help provide Parkinson’s patients and caregivers with knowledge and support to optimize their care through the "Partners in Parkinson's" strategic health initiative launched by The Michael J. Fox Foundation and AbbVie.</p>

        <p>Partners in Parkinson's offers Parkinson's disease (PD) patients and caregivers virtual and face-to-face opportunities to connect with knowledge, tools and support to optimize care from diagnosis through advanced stages of disease.</p>

        <p>The Davis Phinney Foundation (DPF), which has gained the trust and respect of countless people with Parkinson's through its popular <span style="font-style: italic;">The Victory Summit®</span> symposium series and other programs designed to help people with Parkinson's to live well today, will serve as National Presenting Partner. The Davis Phinney Foundation signed on in early 2014, lending its expertise in helping patients live well holistically with Parkinson's disease. As National Presenting Partner, the DPF will lead a breakout session on "Living Well with Parkinson's: A Holistic Approach That Can Benefit You Today and Tomorrow" at each of 11 Partners in Parkinson's events taking place across the United States in 2014. The session will encourage patients to define immediate action steps that may have long-term benefits — including adopting a more active lifestyle and defining a routine to fuel mind and body.</p>

        <p>"The Davis Phinney Foundation is committed to empowering the Parkinson's community to take a proactive role in their care, positively impacting their own outcomes and the lives of those around them," said Polly Dawkins, executive director, The Davis Phinney Foundation. "Collaborating with MJFF, AbbVie and other Parkinson's groups allows the Davis Phinney Foundation to spread our message of holistic wellness as well as share the resources we provide to help people living with Parkinson's disease to live well today. It also shows the community our organizations' shared commitment to improving the quality of life for Parkinson's families at every stage of this disease."</p>

        <p>Partners in Parkinson's also will benefit from the contributions of other national Parkinson's organizations including The Parkinson's Action Network (PAN). As a National Participating Partner, PAN will be present to discuss Parkinson's related policy issues in the resource fair at each event this year. Additionally, Partners in Parkinson's will continue to work with locally-based organizations for each event.  These Partners, from communities across the country, will team up with the program to connect Parkinson's patients with resources in their own backyard.</p>

        <p>"The action-oriented and optimistic messages of The Davis Phinney Foundation and the Parkinson's Action Network are a natural fit for the Partners in Parkinson's program, which aims to provide a wealth of tools and resources to help patients and families live their best lives with Parkinson's," says Todd Sherer, PhD, chief executive officer of The Michael J. Fox Foundation.</p>

        <p>For a full list of 2014 events, to RSVP for an event or to learn more, visit <a href="https://www.partnersinparkinsons.org">www.partnersinparkinsons.org</a>. </p>



        <p><strong>About Partners in Parkinson's</strong></p>
        <p>The Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinson's Research and AbbVie developed Partners in Parkinson's to fill in knowledge gaps by providing new educational tools and resources for the Parkinson's community. The initiative features a comprehensive, educational website with the first online tool to locate a movement disorder specialist, a downloadable Parkinson's disease guide and the opportunity to connect with an AbbVie Parkinson's Disease Advocate for one-on-one support. The program is also designed to connect patients and their families with healthcare and support resources in their own community and will host full-day educational events and resource fairs across the United States.  To learn more about the program visit the website: <a href="https://www.partnersinparkinsons.org">www.partnersinparkinsons.org</a>. </p>

        <p><strong>About The Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinson's Research</strong></p>
        <p>As the world's largest nonprofit funder of Parkinson's research, The Michael J. Fox Foundation is dedicated to accelerating a cure for Parkinson's disease and improved therapies for those living with the condition today. The Foundation pursues its goals through an aggressively funded, highly targeted research program coupled with active global engagement of scientists, Parkinson's patients, business leaders, clinical trial participants, donors and volunteers.  In addition to funding more than $450 million in research to date, the Foundation has fundamentally altered the trajectory of progress toward a cure. Operating at the hub of worldwide Parkinson's research, the Foundation forges groundbreaking collaborations with industry leaders, academic scientists and government research funders; increases the flow of participants into Parkinson's disease clinical trials with its online tool, Fox Trial Finder; promotes Parkinson's awareness through high-profile advocacy, events and outreach; and coordinates the grassroots involvement of thousands of Team Fox members around the world. </p>

        <p>For more information, visit us on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/michaeljfoxfoundation">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/MichaelJFoxOrg">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.michaeljfox.org">Web</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/MJFFlnk">LinkedIn</a>. </p>
      ]]>
    </Content>
    <ArticleDate>2014-07-22T00:00:00.000000-05:00</ArticleDate>
    <ArticleAuthor>Partners in Parkinson's</ArticleAuthor>
    <ArticleImage></ArticleImage>
  </article>




  <article articleId="3" Name="The-Michael-J.-Fox-Foundation-and-AbbVie-launch-Partners-in-Parkinson's" >
    <Title>The Michael J. Fox Foundation and AbbVie launch "Partners in Parkinson's"</Title>
    <metaKeywords></metaKeywords>
    <metaDescription></metaDescription>
    <Header>
      <![CDATA[The Michael J. Fox Foundation and AbbVie launch "Partners in Parkinson's"]]>
    </Header>
    <ShortContent>
      <![CDATA[Nationwide strategic health initiative aims to fill in knowledge gaps and connect patients and caregivers to local resources and one-on-one support]]>
    </ShortContent>
    <Content>
      <![CDATA[
<p>The Michael J. Fox Foundation (MJFF) and AbbVie announced the launch of Partners in Parkinson's, a new strategic health initiative offering comprehensive support to help people with Parkinson's disease (PD) optimize their care at every stage of the disease.</p>
<p>“No two cases of Parkinson's disease are alike. Patients and caregivers need high-quality, trustworthy information and resources that can help navigate a Parkinson's diagnosis and progression,” said Todd Sherer, PhD, chief executive officer of The Michael J. Fox Foundation. “Partners in Parkinson's provides tools to empower the Parkinson's community to take an active role in their own care, now and in the future."</p>

<p>Partners in Parkinson’s provides patients and caregivers with virtual and face-to-face opportunities to connect with knowledge and support. These include an educational website (www.partnersinparkinsons.org) featuring the first online tool enabling patients to locate a movement disorder specialist. The tool was developed in collaboration with the International Parkinson and Movement Disorder Society. The website also connects patients and caregivers with AbbVie Parkinson’s Disease Advocates who are available to provide one-on-one support anywhere in the United States. Finally, the site offers comprehensive information about Parkinson’s, including a downloadable Parkinson’s disease guide..</p>

<p><strong>Fewer than half of Parkinson’s patients know what a movement disorder specialist is</strong></p>
<p>Designed to help Parkinson’s families “discover the benefits of team,” Partners in Parkinson’s is focused in part on the value of specialist care to manage the progressive symptoms and stages of Parkinson’s disease — something too few patients make part of their care regimen. While estimates vary, conventional knowledge holds that the percentage of Parkinson’s patients who ever seek specialist care ranges from 40 to 60 percent. According to a survey conducted online by Harris Poll on behalf of The Michael J. Fox Foundation and AbbVie in February/March 2014 among more than 500 Parkinson’s patients diagnosed with Parkinson’s, as few as 28 percent of Parkinson’s patients are currently seeing a movement disorder specialist (a neurologist with specific training in treating Parkinson’s). Even more tellingly, more than half of patients were unable to identify the correct definition of a movement disorder specialist when given a multiple choice list of definitions. </p>

<p><strong>Filling in knowledge gaps for individuals and the collective</strong></p>
<p>The lack of awareness of specialty care speaks to a large-scale information gap — including a significant lack of knowledge about the progression of Parkinson’s disease. The Michael J. Fox Foundation and AbbVie survey revealed that slightly more than  half (51%) of patients feel “informed or very informed” about what to look for in monitoring Parkinson’s as it progresses, which may hold implications for their ability to appropriately evolve their treatment plans and manage their disease at all stages.</p>

<p>“Partners in Parkinson’s aims to empower patients with the knowledge they need to proactively address care needs from diagnosis through advanced disease,” says Maureen Conley, general manager, neuroscience, AbbVie. “The goal of this initiative is to help Parkinson’s patients and families develop a plan of care that adapts as their symptomatic and lifestyle needs change over time.”</p>
<p>The benefits of taking control of one’s care may go beyond the individual to impact the Parkinson’s community as a whole — because proactive engagement in care often leads to greater engagement in Parkinson’s-related  activities across the board,  less isolation, and in many cases, a decision to participate in clinical trials that urgently need volunteers. For example, the 2014 survey revealed that 81 percent of patients whose main doctor that they see for PD treatment is a movement disorder specialist said they would be “likely or very likely” to participate in a clinical research study if there was one being conducted in their area, compared with 49 percent of patients whose main doctor is a general neurologist and 33 percent of patients whose main doctor is a primary care physician.</p>

<p><strong>Partners in Parkinson’s events</strong></p>
<p>Partners in Parkinson’s will visit 11 cities across the United States in 2014 and 15 cities in 2015. Full-day expos designed for Parkinson’s patients and families feature:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Interactive panels and breakout sessions on understanding Parkinson’s, living well with the disease, and navigating relationships with PD</li>
  <li>The opportunity to witness a typical appointment with a movement disorder specialist firsthand, gaining a sense of the type of information exchange that takes place</li>
  <li>The latest updates on Parkinson’s disease research advances</li>
</ul>

<p>Events also include locally tailored resource fairs to provide convenient “one-stop shopping” for Parkinson’s organizations, activities and local allies of which patients and caregivers may not be aware. The fairs open early and booths will be staffed throughout the day by: </p>
<ul>
  <li>Healthcare providers from local movement disorder centers</li>
  <li>Allied care providers, such as physical and speech therapists, who have experience treating people with Parkinson’s</li>
  <li>Representatives from support and advocacy groups as well as physical activity groups tailored to the needs of people with Parkinson’s</li>
  <li>Clinical trial teams recruiting volunteers for local Parkinson’s research studies</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Who Is Behind Partners in Parkinson’s?</strong></p>
<p>Partners in Parkinson’s has been developed by The Michael J. Fox Foundation and AbbVie. The program reflects both organizations’ commitment to educate and equip patients with resources that help Parkinson’s patients optimize their care at every stage of the disease.</p>

<p>Partners in Parkinson’s also includes the participation of National Presenting Partner The Davis Phinney Foundation who will present a breakout session focused on a holistic approach to living well with Parkinson's at each event this year, National Participating Partner the Parkinson’s Action Network, who will be present Parkinson’s related policy issues in the resource fair at each event this year, and Participating Partners including allied healthcare providers, local organizations and support groups throughout the country. </p>
<p>Partners in Parkinson’s kicked off May 18 in New York City and visits Cleveland on May 31. For a full list of 2014 cities, to RSVP for an event or to learn more, visit www.partnersinparkinsons.org.</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Survey Methodology</strong></p>
<p>This survey was conducted online by Harris Poll on behalf of The Michael J. Fox Foundation and AbbVie from February 4 – March 3, 2014 among 1,530 U.S. adults aged 18+, among whom 528 are patients diagnosed with Parkinson’s disease at age 30+, 500 are caregivers of patients with Parkinson’s disease and 502 are physicians who currently treat at least 5 patients who have Parkinson’s disease. In an effort to ensure that survey results would be indicative of the general Parkinson’s population (among whom the average age of diagnosis is 60), the answers of 22 adults who self-reported diagnosis with Parkinson’s prior to age 30 were discarded. Among the physicians, 202 are primary care physicians (PCPs) and 300 are neurologists. Among the neurologists, 119 identify themselves as movement disorder specialists and 181 are general neurologists (defined as neurologists who did not self-identify as a movement disorder specialist). For a complete methodology, including weighting variables, please and a list of topline results, visit <a href="https://www.partnersinparkinsons.org" target="_self">www.partnersinparkinsons.org</a>.</p>

<br />
<p style="font-size:11px;">* Small base (n=70) and results should be interpreted as directional in nature.</p>
]]>
    </Content>
    <ArticleDate>2014-05-27T00:00:00.000000-05:00</ArticleDate>
    <ArticleAuthor>Partners in Parkinson's</ArticleAuthor>
    <ArticleImage></ArticleImage>
  </article>






  <article articleId="4" Name="partners-in-parkinsons-harris-poll-Topline-results" >
	<Title>Partners in Parkinson’s Harris Poll: Topline Results</Title>
	<metaKeywords></metaKeywords>
	<metaDescription></metaDescription>
	<Header>
	  <![CDATA[Partners in Parkinson’s Harris Poll: Topline Results]]>
	</Header>
	<ShortContent>
	  <![CDATA[New survey reveals knowledge gap among Parkinson’s patients about progression of Parkinson’s disease and the benefits of seeking specialty care]]>
	</ShortContent>
	<Content>
	  <![CDATA[
<p>In May 2014, The Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinson’s Research (MJFF) and AbbVie launched Partners in Parkinson’s, a new strategic health initiative directed at Parkinson’s patients and caregivers with the goal of filling knowledge gaps and better equipping individuals and families to navigate a Parkinson’s diagnosis and progression.</p>
<p>Through their respective work with the Parkinson’s community, both MJFF and AbbVie hold key beliefs that (1) patients and caregivers are living with significant knowledge gaps in their understanding of Parkinson’s disease and its progression; (2) too few patients seek out specialty and/or allied care in order to help optimize their care and (3) under-use of specialty care has implications for both individuals and the community as a whole.</p>
<p>Harris Poll conducted a survey in early 2014 on behalf of The Michael J. Fox Foundation and AbbVie to help better understand patients’ and caregivers’ attitudes and knowledge on these themes. Topline results of the survey follow.</p>

<p><strong>Patients are under-informed about treatments for their current Parkinson’s disease (PD) symptoms, and about how the disease may progress in the future.</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Only about half of Parkinson’s patients reported they feel “informed” or “very informed” about treatments for motor symptoms (54%) and for non-motor symptoms (46%).</li>
  <li>57% of patients said they are “informed” or “very informed” about Parkinson’s progression.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>There is low awareness among Parkinson’s patients and caregivers about the role of a movement disorder specialist.</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Fewer than half of patients (48%) were able to identify role of a movement disorder specialist when given a multiple choice list of definitions.</li>
  <li>Only 28% of Parkinson’s patients are currently being treated by a movement disorder specialist and fewer than half (45%) have ever seen a movement disorder specialist.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>However, based on patients who see a movement disorder specialist, there are benefits to seeking this type of care.</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Patients who see a movement disorder specialist as their main doctor are significantly more informed about basic issues in managing Parkinson’s disease, including:
	  <ul>
		  <li>Diagnosis of PD (89% of patients who see a movement disorder specialist; 70% who see a general neurologist; 56%* who see a PCP)</li>
		  <li>PD in general (92% of patients who see a movement disorder specialist; 66% who see a general neurologist; 60%* who see a PCP)</li>
		  <li>PD progression (76% of patients who see a movement disorder specialist; 54% who see a general neurologist; 52%* who see a PCP)</li>
	  </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Patients who see a movement disorder specialist as their main doctor are more likely than those who see a PCP or general neurologist as their main doctor to have a comprehensive dialogue about PD topics, saying their doctor/nurse talks to them at most visits or at every visit about:
	  <ul>
		  <li>How I am feeling physically (91% of patients who see a movement disorder specialist; 83% who see a general neurologist; 65%* who see a PCP)</li>
		  <li>How PD is impacting my life (75% of patients who see a movement disorder specialist; 58% who see a general neurologist; 45%* who see a PCP)</li>
		  <li>The role of exercise in managing PD (78% of patients who see a movement disorder specialist; 56% who see a general neurologist; 40%* who see a PCP)</li>
		  <li>Referrals to other health care professionals (44% of patients who see an movement disorder specialist; 25% who see a general neurologist; 36%* who see a PCP)</li>
	  </ul>
  </li>

  <p><strong>Taking a proactive role in one’s own care by seeking specialty care can lead to more engagement in the Parkinson’s community overall, including participating in research.</strong></p>
  <ul>
	  <li>Many more patients who currently see a movement disorder specialist (54%) feel “informed” or “very informed” about opportunities to participate in clinical research, compared to patients who have never heard of or seen a movement disorder specialist (13%).</li>
	  <li>More patients whose main doctor for their PD is a movement disorder specialist (37%) reported their doctor talked to them about clinical research participation opportunities at every or most visits, compared to patients whose main doctor for their PD is a general neurologist (17%) or a primary care physician* (15%).</li>
  </ul>

  <div style="font-size:11px;">
	  <p><strong>Survey Methodology</strong><br />
		The survey referenced in this article was conducted online within the United States by Harris Poll on behalf of The Michael J. Fox Foundation and AbbVie from February 4 – March 3, 2014 among 1,530 adults age 18 and older, among which 528 are patients diagnosed with Parkinson’s disease at age 30+, 500 are caregivers of patients with Parkinson’s disease and 502 are physicians who currently treat at least 5 patients who have Parkinson’s disease.  In an effort to ensure that survey results would be indicative of the general Parkinson’s population (among whom the average age of diagnosis is 60), the answers of 22 adults who self-reported diagnosis with Parkinson’s prior to age 30 were discarded. Among the physicians, 202 are primary care physicians (PCPs) and 300 are neurologists. Among the neurologists, 119 identify themselves as movement disorder specialists (movement disorder specialists) and 181 are general neurologists (defined as neurologists who did not self-identify as a movement disorder specialists).
	  </p>
	  <p>Among the patient and caregiver sample, figures for gender, race/ethnicity, education, region, household income, severity of loved one’s PD, current age and age of onset were weighted where necessary to bring them into line with their actual proportions in the population. Respondents for the patients and caregivers survey were selected from among those who have agreed to participate in Harris Poll surveys. Because this sample is based on those who agreed to participate in the panel, no estimates of theoretical sampling error can be calculated. </p>
	  <p>Among the physician sample, physicians were mailed a letter inviting them to participate in the online survey. All physician contact information was randomly pulled from the AMA Masterfile. Data are weighted where necessary by region, years in practice by gender, and specialty to bring them in line with their actual proportions in the population. </p>
	  <p>All sample surveys and polls, whether or not they use probability sampling, are subject to multiple sources of error which are most often not possible to quantify or estimate, including sampling error, coverage error, error associated with nonresponse, error associated with question wording and response options, and post-survey weighting and adjustments. Therefore, we avoid the words “margin of error” as they are misleading. All that can be calculated are different possible sampling errors with different probabilities for pure, unweighted, random samples with 100% response rates. These are only theoretical because no published polls come close to this ideal. </p>
  </div>
  
  
  
<br />
<p style="font-size:11px;">* Small base (n=70) and results should be interpreted as directional in nature</p>  
]]>
	</Content>
	<ArticleDate>2014-05-19T00:00:00.000000-05:00</ArticleDate>
	<ArticleAuthor>Partners in Parkinson’s</ArticleAuthor>
	<ArticleImage></ArticleImage>
  </article>

  
  
  
  
  
  <article articleId="5" Name="New Educational Program Partners in Parkinson's to Kick Off in New York City on May 18" >
    <Title>New Educational Program Partners in Parkinson's to Kick Off in New York City on May 18</Title>
    <metaKeywords></metaKeywords>
    <metaDescription>Kicking off next month, Partners in Parkinson's will bring educational tools and resources directly to patients in 11 U.S. cities in 2014.</metaDescription>
    <Header>
      <![CDATA[New Educational Program Partners in Parkinson's to Kick Off in New York City on May 18]]>
    </Header>
    <ShortContent>
      <![CDATA[Kicking off next month, Partners in Parkinson's will bring educational tools and resources directly to patients in 11 U.S. cities in 2014.]]>
    </ShortContent>
    <Content>
      <![CDATA[<p>The Michael J. Fox Foundation and AbbVie have partnered to create <a href="http://www.partnersinparkinsons.org/">Partners in Parkinson’s</a>, a strategic health initiative to fill knowledge gaps and provide new educational tools and resources for the Parkinson’s community to help optimize care at every stage of disease. Beginning in New York City on May 18 and Cleveland on May 31, Partners in Parkinson’s will visit 11 cities across the United States in 2014.</p>
<p><b>Understanding Your Parkinson’s<br /></b>Navigating a Parkinson’s diagnosis and progression can be complex.<b> </b> Partners in Parkinson’s events will provide patients and caregivers with valuable resources and information for living well with Parkinson’s disease. Through a full-day schedule of panel discussions, Partners in Parkinson’s events will offer new insights on topics including:</p>
<p></p>
<ul>
<li>How to make the most of your relationship with your doctor, and what to expect from specialist care</li>
<li>Updates on research toward new treatments for Parkinson’s, and opportunities to participate in studies that need you</li>
<li>How Parkinson’s affects relationships with family, friends, spouse — and strategies for keeping these vital connections strong</li>
<li>How engaging in the Parkinson’s community can help others as well as yourself</li>
</ul>
<p><b>Collaboration is key<br /></b>In addition to structured panel discussions, Partners in Parkinson’s also provides the opportunity to browse a full-day, local Resource Fair. The fair will help you learn more about the resources available in your local Parkinson’s community — including movement disorder specialists, clinical trials, allied healthcare providers (such as physical, speech and occupational therapists), political advocacy groups, support groups and more.  </p>
<p>By attending panel discussions and the resource fair, patients and caregivers can learn about building a team of care providers that will help them understand their Parkinson’s disease and take an active role in managing their care, benefitting them today and in the future.</p>
<p>Join The Michael J. Fox Foundation and AbbVie at the Grand Hyatt in New York City on May 18 for the inaugural Partners in Parkinson’s event. Visit <a href="http://www.partnersinparkinsons.org/">www.partnersinparkinsons.org</a> to RSVP today. </p>

]]>
    </Content>
    <ArticleDate>2014-04-07T00:00:00.000000-05:00</ArticleDate>
    <ArticleAuthor>Partners in Parkinson's</ArticleAuthor>
    <ArticleImage></ArticleImage>
  </article>
  
  
</articles>